《斯巴达克斯：血与沙》
《政党恩惠》
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!
他们在呐喊你的名字
They roar your name.
用不了多久 他们也会呐喊你的名字
Soon they shall roar yours as well.
但如果你心不在焉的话 大概就只能赚到哀嚎了
Or mourn it, if your mind is absent the task.
我的妻儿至今下落不明…
I'm yet to have word on my wife and son…
我才不要一个
I will not fight alongside a man
弄不清自己目标的搭档
who is not clear to his purpose.
我很清楚
I am clear.
我的目标是血流成河
My purpose is blood.
举盾！！
Shield!!
哦 太棒了！
Oh yes!
尽管搭档是个不入流的角斗士
Even chained to an inferior gladiator,
斯巴达克斯仍战无不胜！
Spartacus prevails!
卡普亚冠军的身上 从来不乏惊奇之事！
One would expect no less from the Champion of Capua!
且看他如何让民众沸腾！
See how he ignites the crowd!
他现身于贵公子生日会一事
His presence at your son's birthday
将成为共和国的美谈
will be the talk of the Republic.
哈！
Ha!
这和我15岁时有天壤之别
A far cry from my own fifteenth year.
穿上成人礼袍 我便成人了
When I put on the Toga Virilis and passed into manhood,
仪式虽然正式 却沉闷无比
it was a stuffy, formal ceremony
乏味得像是巫婆和亡灵的对谈
ridden with corpses and hags.
我父亲自称是个演说家
My father deemed himself an orator.
却说得宾客昏昏欲睡 有些人甚至睡死了过去！
Lulled our guests to slumber, some never to awaken!
对Numerius 我们绝不能如此
We would not have it so for Numerius.
他吵着要你手下最好的两个角斗士
He's been clamoring for a pair of your finest,
在他的成人礼上
to battle in exhibition
来场精彩对决
at his celebration.
我们一定得满足他这个心愿
Well we would see him well satisfied.
当然 也得令他尊贵的父亲满意
And by extension his noble father.
如果您能在鄙陋室
Though thought strikes if you hold the celebration
举办这场庆典
beneath my humble roof,
那么 贵公子就能近观我旗下每一个角斗士了
then your boy can bear close witness to all my gladiators.
可以吗 父亲？拜托了？！
Could we, Father? Please?!
这么做 要多花多少钱？
And the extra cost for such generosity?
朋友之间 举手之劳
A favor between friends.
那真是感激不尽！
Received with much gratitude!
啊！
Uh!
斯巴达克斯 下一个就轮到你了
You're next Spartacus.
到这儿来啊
Come here.
你确定 这不会不合适吗？
Are you certain it won't cause imposition?
千万别这么想
Place it from your thoughts.
成人礼一生只有一次
A boy becomes a man but once in his life.
无论他有什么愿望 都应该得到满足
He should be richly indulged in his interests.
他对角斗赛百看不厌
He never ceases to tire of the games.
对于鲜血和竞技
He's of the same obsessive ilk as Ilithyia
他和Ilithyia是同一类人
regarding blood and sport.
她的缺席倒令人惊讶
Her absence comes as surprise.
莫非她一声不响地 已经回罗马去了？
Has she returned to Rome, absent farewells?
没
No.
她觉得… 不舒服
She has been feeling… unwell.
希望不会太严重吧？
Nothing serious, I hope?
不过是胃不舒服 静养下就没事了
It will pass, as all things born of a weak stomach.
他的战袍让我们无从下手
His armor gives pause.
那我们应该攻击高位
Then we shall aim higher.
拉！
Pull!
哦！
Oh!
哦耶！
Oh yeah!
我从没见过这么精彩的一幕！
I've never seen anything like it!
耶！！
Yeah!!
起来
Get up.
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!
留着精力 来日再战
Live to fight another day.
看到别人冠着你的称号 真让我难受
It pains me to watch others claim your laurels.
如果你一直站在我旁边 你会更难受
Your pain shall increase if you continue to stand beside me.
做得好 兄弟
Yeah, well done brother.
干得漂亮
Well done.
你今天状态不错
You fought well today.
蒙天神眷顾 有你这么个搭档
The gods favored me, to count you as ally.
他们的眷顾 可不光局限在竞技场内哦
Their favor extends beyond the arena.
Aurelia啊…
Aurelia…
啊 我真怕我再也见不到你了
Ah, I feared I would never hold you again.
当我让Ashur送信给你的时候
Ashur said he found only blood
他说 他只找到一滩血迹
when I sent him to you with message.
Titus回来了
Titus had returned.
他没伤着你吧？
Did he hurt you?
我等着他被五马分尸的那一天…
I will see his heart from his fucking chest…
那滩血不是我的
The blood was not mine.
我狠狠地刺伤了他的下体
I cut him, deep and low.
他再也不能强奸妇女了
He will never force himself on a woman again.
然后 我就跑到山上的哥哥家
Afterwards I sought refuge
避难去了
with my brother's family, in the hills.
在斯巴达克斯的指示下
The slave girl found me there,
女奴发现了我
by Spartacus' direction.
感谢天神 你平安无事
Thank the gods you're safe.
当Titus首次将魔爪伸向我的时候 天神在哪儿？
Where were they when Titus first laid hands on me?
我还怀着他的孩子
I still carry his child.
什么也没变 Varro
Nothings changed, Varro.
整个世界都变了
The entire world has changed.
我也变了
And I along with it.
孩子
The child.
是你孕育的 属于你的一部分
It springs from your belly, a part of you.
如果你想要他的话…
I would love it as such…
我会爱他如同己出
if you would have it so.
有人发现了你的缺席
Your absence was noticed.
缺席…？
Absence…?
竞技赛
The games.
你本来应该和我们在一起的
You were supposed to join us.
我不敢面对窥视的眼睛
I could not face prying eyes.
只要别人一看我的眼睛 他们就会了解一切
One look into mine and they would have full knowledge.
Licinia的血…
Licinia's blood…
她的头骨在我的掌中碎裂…
Her skull steeped between my fingers…
拜托 你能不能清醒一点！
Jupiter's cock, would you come to grips!
Licinia的死 和你那档子事
Licinia's murder and your part in it,
早被遮得严严实实
have been concealed.
真相绝不会泄露
The truth will only unfold if,
除非你自己失声说了出来
if your jaw splits and your tongue unfurls in song.
你想让我这样吗？
Would you have me do?
做回你自己吧
Appear yourself,
没事别玩什么良心谴责了
absent conscience of deeds unknown.
行政官的庆典
The Magistrate's celebration
正是一个良机
provides a perfect opportunity.
庆典将在我家举行
The venue turns to my husband as host.
你甚至可以待着不动
You won't even have to move from under this roof,
我会帮你重塑信心
my hand ever present to steady your resolve.
你能帮我过这一关？
You will guide me through this?
我们是挚友啊
As trusted friend.
作为挚友 你也得回报我吧
And as such, I require favor.
我们联手让这次庆典
We would swell the ranks of celebration
成为罗马贵族的盛宴
with these noble citizens.
我肯定贵族们会乐意接受
Ones I am certain would accept invite
Albinius元老院议员之女的邀请
from the daughter of Senator Albinius.
振作起来
Gather yourself.
很多大事等着你呢
And see it done.
欠你的人情 我这一辈子也还不了
I owe you more than I can ever repay.
如果你没有派Mira去找我妻子…
If you had not sent Mira to find my wife…
她回心转意了 对吧？
She has taken you back, then?
我也成为不了那个配得上她的男人
And I will yet be the man she deserves.
如果成不了 我就天天在你耳边数落你的缺点
If not, I shall remind you of your shortcomings.
哦 看见一个男人和妻子团聚
Oh. It lifts the heart.
这真叫人激动
To see a man reunited with his woman.
现在 你不必担心死的时候
Now you'll have someone to weep for you
没人为你哭坟了
when you die.
如果我要死 也要死在竞技场上
If I fall, it will be in the arena.
作为角斗士而死
As a gladiator.
你肯定还记得这种感觉 对吧？
You remember what that is like, do you not?
斯巴达克斯 Crixus
Spartacus, Crixus.
主人传召你们
You are summoned.
让我俩对阵？
We are to fight each other?
是Numerius的要求
Numerius has chosen.
他坚持要亲眼见证
He insisted on drinking in the spectacle
当今战神与过去战神的交锋
of present glories pitted against the past.
他的愿望 当然应该得到满足 主人
And his thirst shall be satisfied, Dominus.
记住 这只是一次表演
Keep to mind this is an exhibition.
可能会有流血 但仅仅是为了助兴
Blood may be spilled, but only for show.
谁胆敢一发而不可收拾
Serious punishment will be meeted out
我一定会严惩不贷
to the man who caused them.
我们会为您争光的 主人
We shall serve you with honor, Dominus.
最好如此
I expect no less.
回住处去吧
Return to quarters.
斯巴达克斯 留一下
Spartacus, remain.
你对Crixus怎么看？
What make you of Crixus?
Numerius坚持要他上场
Numerius insisted upon him,
但他的伤口才刚刚愈合…
yet with his wounds barely sealed…
他认为自己已经痊愈了
He believes himself ready.
自欺欺人
To a fault.
自尊受到的打击 远胜于肉体
The ego bruises deeper than the flesh.
前不久 他才给我们家族带来无上荣耀
He brought this house great honor, not long ago.
别让他太过尴尬了
Do not overly embarrass the man.
我会给Numerius演场戏
I will give Numerius a show.
再无其它
Nothing more.
我当年穿上成人礼服的时候 正是在这间屋子
When I put on the Toga Virilis, it was in this very room,
身边围满了我父亲的勇士
surrounded by my father's champions.
那时我就知道
Even then I knew
有朝一日 我自己的勇士 将会令他们黯然失色
that one day my own Titans would eclipse them all.
Spartacus 送雨的使者 这荣耀非你莫属
None more so than Spartacus, the Bringer of Rain.
瞧啊？
Ugh?
你让我荣光无限
You honor me.
谁也没你的功劳大
You stand above all others.
继续保持这势头 我们将把世界尽收囊中…
Continue on this path, and we will have the world…
啊！
Grrrr!
你在躲我
You have been avoiding me.
我正在做事呢
I have been tending my duties.
你这态度冷冰冰的
Your manner hardens.
我还是喜欢你微笑的样子 前不久我们还相处甚欢…
I prefer it soft, as the moment we shared not so long ago…
你误会我的笑容了 肢体碰触也是善意的
You mistake smile and friendly touch beyond intent.
那么 在你「善意」的碰触之后
And the key that went missing from my clasp,
我那把不翼而飞的钥匙呢？
after your "friendly" touch?
它不会是被你误拾了去吧？
It did not by "mistake" draw into your palm, did it?
不是
It did not.
这问题让你这么紧张啊
And yet you tense from question.
这种反应让人有理由进行搜身…
Such reaction warrants fair search…
我只效忠于主人
My hands service Domina alone.
未经允许 她不会乐意见到
She would not be pleased to have yours
我被别人搜身
laid upon me without her consent.
或者知道有个守卫丢了钥匙
Or to learn a guard has misplaced his key.
我不会让这事发生的
I would not have it so.
你可是因玩弄女人 而享负盛名啊
You have reputation for your handling of women.
到她们身上寻求慰藉去吧
Seek your loss among them,
别用这种破理由来逼我
and do not press me again with accusation.
你确定Ilithyia在行政官面前…
You trust Ilithyia not to come unhinged…
不会乱发疯？
in front of the Magistrate?
我会死死盯住她的
I shall keep watchful eyes upon her.
但愿这次你能盯牢点儿
More watchful than the last, I pray.
一切对我们大为有利啊
Everything worked to our advantage.
Ilithyia也欠我们债 这些债务结算下来
Ilithyia's in our debt, and through collection
我们自可铸就家族盛世
we gained access to the most noble of families.
是她拟的名单？
She attends to the list?
她将为行政官的典礼 盛邀宾朋
She will draw all to the Magistrate's celebration,
巧妙地引他们来我们这里作客
so artfully placed within our walls.
不得有任何差错啊
There must be no cause for disappointment.
在斯巴达克斯和Crixus的表演赛
After the exhibition between Spartacus and Crixus
让行政官的儿子尽兴之后
has ignited his son,
我会向行政官 提一下参政的事
I will broach the Magistrate on subject of political office.
肯定会得到同意
And be well received.
哈！
Ha!
Solonius看到我 和卡普亚最上层人员互通往来
To behold Solonius' face when he sees me
该是怎样一副嘴脸
consort with the highest echelon of Capua.
Solonius吗？
Solonius?
他如何目睹这一切？
Well how should he witness such a thing?
我会邀请他来
By invitation.
我要让他亲眼看到
I desire his eyes upon me
行政官对我青眼有加
when I am anointed by the Magistrate.
我要让他看到我财运亨通
I want him to see that as my fortunes rise,
他却人财两空
his plummet.
你要往蛇的伤口上撒盐
You taunt an injured snake.
而这条蛇 随时可能反咬一口
One that may yet turn and strike.
别担心
Ease your mind.
到时候 我会让这条大蛇
The serpent's head will be struck from its body
身首异处
in due course.
哈 Solonius没机会反击的
Ha, and Solonius will never see it coming.
那 你和Crixus只是演戏 是吗？
So, you and Crixus battling as entertainment, eh?
演一场让那孩子永生难忘的戏
Something the boy will never forget.
只是表演而已
It is only exhibition.
主人严令不可重伤对手
Dominus gave strict instructions to avoid grievous injury.
你可别相信他会听话
Do not believe he was listening.
你们的高卢角斗士已然康复了嘛
Your Gaul is restored.
康复的可不止他一个人
He is not alone.
黑夜过去 阳光普照 将使万物复苏
The sun has revived what the night had withered.
有赖于一位挚友的厚意
Due to kindness of a dear friend.
这份厚意有回报了吗？
And is that kindness returned?
行政官的典礼 将因名单上的人的参与
The Magistrate's celebration will swell
而大放光芒
with all names provided.
非常感谢
Gratitude.
我会倾全力 为这事添砖加瓦的
Would that I had words to multiply it in response.
朋友的价值
Yet the value of a friend
不是用文字可以表达的
cannot be expressed by the clever grouping of letters.
是这血肉之躯
It is blood and flesh,
使世间彰显生机
granting life to the world.
你像个贱女一样服服帖帖
You submit like a fucking girl,
等着男人给你开苞呢
begging for a cock to split her open.
我输了 你要我怎么做？
I was bested. What would you have me do?
站起身来 一息尚存 战斗不止
Rise and fight till your final breath.
不然就说明 所谓「兄弟」之名只是虚假
Or prove the name "brother" false.
听说西西里岛处处有生机
Heard of opportunities in Sicilia.
要是我聪明点儿 我们早该逃去那里
Had I been wise, we would have moved there
甩掉一切债务了
to escape my debts.
然而我妻子的忠告 却被我抛之脑后
Yet the advice of my wife fell short of its mark.
女人的话 要让男人听进去
It is a distance to travel,
可不是那么容易呢
from a woman's mouth to a man's ears.
从此刻起 我会听她的话的
I shall close the gap, from this point forward.
Aurelia告诉我 西西里岛受神灵庇佑
Aurelia tells me Sicilia is an island blessed by the gods.
你重获自由后 一定要到那里来找我们
You must visit us there, when you gain freedom.
我不再奢望逃离此处
I no longer concern myself with thoughts beyond these walls.
你也不该那样想
And nor should you.
一位真正的战神 应心系竞技场
A true champion dreams only of the arena.
倘若那人不再是战神 他又该心系何处呢？
And what does one dream of when he's no longer champion?
从那窃取名号的小偷手中
Regaining the title from the thief
夺回头衔
who stole it from me.
他什么也没偷
He stole nothing.
如果我是窃贼 全卡普亚民众都能作证
If I am a thief, the crime was witnessed by all of Capua.
可我现今依然享负盛誉
And is still celebrated to this day.
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!
主人传唤你
You are summoned.
行政官明日
The Magistrate will arrive tomorrow
将赶在其客人之前到达
well in advance of his guests,
以确保一切筹备合乎标准
to ensure that preparations are to his standards.
等我让他满意后 那个孩子将交由你照料
While I reassure him, I would have you tend the boy.
务必迎合他的心意
It's imperative that he is well satisfied,
并尽量满足他那尊贵的父亲
and by proximity his noble father.
我会为Batiatus之名争光的
The name Batiatus will be honored.
让共和国上下为之眼红
And envied throughout the Republic.
这一招棋很不明智
You move unwisely.
你会玩？
You play?
我玩过这个
I've had occasion,
那时我尚在后备军服役
during my time with the auxiliary.
尽管彰显你的博识吧
By all means, grace us with your knowledge.
嗯
Mm.
看来 我们的战神不擅长玩
It appears our champion has no head
战略游戏啊
for games of strategy.
嗯 一场战役的失败…
Mm, battles maybe lost…
并不能阻碍整场战争的胜利落幕啊
and yet the war concludes in victory.
哈！真他妈狡诈
Ahh! Treacherous fuck.
像个真正的罗马人一样战斗吧
Played like a true Roman.
腾出椅子来 去给我们拿些酒
Fall from your chair. And bring us wine.
叙利亚人做起生意来 能骗倒神鬼
The Syrian could swindle the scales from a snake,
却不善攻术
but never command a charge.
来啊！
Come!
让我们来进行男人之间的较量…
Let us have contest between men…
哦 我想念你的抚摸
Oh, your touch has been missed.
我的整个脑海为你占据
And thoughts of yours consume me.
不久 你就能感觉到战神的双手
Soon you will feel the hands of a champion
再次触碰你的身体
once again upon you.
跟斯巴达克斯的比赛只是场表演
The match with Spartacus is but exhibition.
我知道观众们想要什么
I know the crowd as my heart.
他们渴望鲜血 我就给他们鲜血
They will yearn for blood, and I shall give it to them.
主人不允许有人受伤
Dominus forbids injury.
想取斯巴达克斯的命 你就必须得…
To make attempt on Spartacus' life is to…
赌上自己的命啊
is to risk your own.
这就是我的命运啊
This is my life.
如果不是战神 那我什么都不是
If not Champion, I am nothing.
那我要是去爱那个战神
Then I must be without my mind,
肯定会把我逼疯的
to love only the man.
没错
Yes.
而我爱的 就是你的疯狂
And I relish your madness.
啊！真他妈要命啊！
Ah! Fuck the heavens!
你是怎么能战无不胜的啊？
How can you keep besting a man so far above your station?
我生来 手里就握着利剑
I sprung from my mother with sword in hand.
战斗技能是我的第二天性
The ways of battle are second nature,
这是家族的遗传
passed down from father to son.
我真遗憾我父亲没有看到
I regret my own father never saw the advantage
军事的荣耀之处
of military glory.
从来都没发现 它能带来的好处
Never saw the spoils that could be won.
为了资助人和盟约 他拿起了武器
The patronage, the alliances forged had he taken up arms.
他从来没有过什么大的追求
He aspired to be no further than what he was.
只是远离罗马城的一个 简单角斗士主而已
A simple lanista, far from Rome.
而我和你
You and I, however.
我们已经长上了翅膀 可以飞翔
We have fashioned wings, to raise us higher
不至于陷入先辈们那肮脏的泥潭里
than the muck and mire of heritage.
高飞到先辈们无法想象的地方
Higher than our fathers could never imagine.
Quintus啊？
Quintus?
是什么吵醒了夫人的美梦啊？
What stirs such a vision from her dreams?
我的丈夫不在身边
My husband not beside me.
斯巴达克斯在陪我练棋呢
Spartacus was helping me hone my game.
还喝着小酒？… 哼嗯！
Over a cup of wine?… Hmm!
感谢你的指导
Gratitude for the instruction.
你脑子没病吧？
Have your senses flown?
居然跟一个奴隶一起喝酒…
To share drink with a slave…
我是在和卡普亚战神一起喝酒
I drink with the Champion of Capua.
Crixus曾是战神
Crixus was Champion.
但你从没想过和他喝杯酒
Yet no cup was ever raised with him.
咳啊！
Argh!
Crixus只是个蛮人
Crixus is a brute.
可斯巴达克斯不同
Spartacus is different.
我们的好财运 可都是靠着他呢
We owe our good fortune to the man.
他是个下贱的奴隶啊
He's beneath you
明天我们就要招待卡普亚的大官了
and tomorrow we play host to Capua's finest.
这种行为会让人轻视的
Such behavior would be spat upon.
他们不耻的只会是他们自己的阳具
They spit only to stroke their own cocks.
因为有斯巴达克斯 行政官才会恩宠我们
Spartacus is the reason the Magistrate graces our house,
我们才能拥有他带来的权势
along with all the shits that follow.
他们来看的是你
They come to see you.
一个平步青云的男人
A man ascended to the heavens.
而斯巴达克斯只不过是 你骑在胯下的野兽而已
And Spartacus is merely the beast that you ride upon.
你跟Varro像兄弟一样作战
You and Varro fought as if brothers.
你们的胜利无比荣耀
Your victory was a glorious sight.
你看到钥匙了吗 啊？
Did you see the key, huh?
啊？
Huh?
装作好像什么都不知道的样子？啊？
Don't suppose you know anything about that? Huh?
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
闭嘴
Still your tongue.
那女人惹到你什么了？
What grievance has the woman given?
跟你没关系
None which concerns you.
我认识她
She is known to me.
这儿的每个男人都认识她
This one is known to every cock in the villa.
滚开
Move off.
告诉我她怎么惹你了
Tell me her grievance.
我下过命令了
I gave you command.
停下！
Stop!
都他妈的在干什么？
What is the fucking meaning of this?
说话啊！
Speak!
你的守卫无缘无故殴打Mira
Your man attacks Mira without cause.
你凭什么 胆敢
What reason have you for laying hands
对我的奴隶动手？
on one of my slaves?
这女孩是个贼
The girl is a thief.
我什么都没偷过！
I stole nothing!
那你觉得她偷了什么呢？
What exactly do you believe she has stolen?
不值钱的东西
Nothing of worth.
滚
Go.
你做得太过了
You overstep.
这月的工钱 别拿了
A month's wages, forfeited.
要是敢再犯 就不只是扣扣小钱而已了
Press further and coin will be replaced by blood.
滚吧
Remove yourself.
是 主人
Dominus.
恕罪
Apologies.
别他妈的废话！
Do not fucking speak!
我刚在妻子面前帮你说话
I defend your worth to my wife,
你就在我的房子里搞这些个玩意
only to turn and find you shitting in my fucking house.
如果成年礼不是在明天的话
If the Toga Virilis were not tomorrow,
我早用鞭子把你揍得
I would have you lashed until the flesh peeled
皮开肉绽了
from your back.
再敢跟我的警卫动手
Lay hands on one of my guards again,
你会更惨不忍睹
and you will receive far worse.
明白 主人
Dominus.
你打了一个守卫 却没被罚？
You attack a guard yet escape punishment?
战神名号可不是用来看的
Being Champion is not without advantage.
看来我以后得紧紧跟在你后面了啊
I must remember to stay close to your side.
也许你的好运会分点到我身上
Perhaps a swath of your good fortune will rub off upon me.
要是你多花些力气
Your efforts would be better focused
保护你的侧面就好了
protecting your flank.
哦 该死！
Oh, fuck!
Calavius行政官！
Magistrate Calavius!
Batiatus家欢迎您的到来
The House of Batiatus welcomes you,
真是蓬荜生辉啊！
on this glorious day!
年轻的男孩走进来 出门就变成男子汉了！
A young boy enters my doors, but leaves a man!
感谢你的款待
Gratitude for your hospitalities.
我们会铭记于心的
We are in your debt.
我们都会的
As are we all.
Ilithyia啊！
Ilithyia!
我很担心你的健康啊
I'd begun to fear for your health.
小小问题而已
A momentary lapse.
我可真是受到了无微不至的关怀啊
I've been tended to with most compassionate care
就在这个地方
within these walls.
角斗士们呢？
Where are the gladiators?
Numerius啊
Numerius.
他昨晚因为过度兴奋而无法入睡
He couldn't sleep last night, for excitement.
谁能为此责怪他呢？！
Who can blame him?!
站在共和国最伟大的巨人们中间
To stand among the greatest titans
他们都将遵从你的号令
of the Republic, his to command.
我？真的吗？
Mine? Really?
我授命每一位光荣的勇士
Each of my proud warriors has been instructed
都遵从你的号令 如同遵从我一般
to regard your orders as if from my own lips.
Flavius肯定会嫉妒死的
Flavius will be filled with great envy.
活该他嫉妒！
As he should!
当他听闻卡普亚战神 亲自带你参观训练场的时候
Even more so when he hears the Champion of Capua himself
还不知会嫉妒到哪里去呢
has given you a tour of the ludus.
斯巴达克斯？
Spartacus?!
他正等待你的驾临 在你父亲的许可之下…
He awaits your presence, with permission of your father…
统治这些阿波罗战马般的勇士 我将更有财运
I would have better fortune reigning Apollo's horses.
守卫！护送年轻的Numerius
Guards! Escort young Numerius
到训练场
to the training square.
我从未见过他如此兴致昂扬
I've never seen him in higher spirits.
Batiatus家的别墅的确拥有这样的魅力
The house of Batiatus has such an effect.
你曾站在他们的阳台眺望过吗？
Have you ever witnessed a view from their balcony?
那里的景色将彻底征服你的感官
It simply overwhelms the senses.
来吧
Come.
我们去注视卡普亚的完美艺术品吧
Let us gaze upon Capua's perfection.
也给两个大男人一些私人时间
And give the men private moment
探讨彼此的女人 如何风骚迷人
to discuss how ravishing their women are.
Ilithyia住在你这里？
Ilithyia resides with you?
暂时如此
For the moment.
是我们重要的朋友
A valued friend.
父亲与丈夫均与元老院关系匪浅
With connection to the senate in both husband and father.
确实价值重大
Value indeed.
每一个人 都必须非常小心得挑选伙伴
One must choose one's company with exceeding care.
否则 就等着被拖后腿吧
Or else be dragged down by them.
一切准备妥当了？
Preparations are in order?
我已将这孩子视如己出
Set as if the boy was my own.
无须多虑
Erase all concern.
今夜 将让所有出席者
This night will be etched in the memories of
此生铭记
all in attendance.
这该是怎样的感觉 在你的手心
What is it like, having the life of another
攥着另一个生命？
resting in your hands?
我兴许能一剑 终结他的性命
My sword may deliver the final blow,
但是一名角斗士的命运
but a gladiator's fate is for the crowd
要由观众和主人所决定
and the editor to decide.
这悬崖处没有墙啊！
You have no wall over by the cliff!
正是因为这一点 我才觉得最好不要在此地训练
The very reason I find it best not to train there.
有人曾掉下悬崖吗？
Has anyone ever fallen below?
我曾亲眼目睹过一次
I've witnessed but one.
来吧
Come.
上次一别 我们已经很久没有训练了
It's been a long time since last we trained.
看看你还记得多少
Let us see what you remember.
行政官的儿子让我们的战地遍洒荣光…
The Magistrate's son graces our sands…
而我们就这样迎接他？
and this is what greets him?
为了配得上他的兴致 我需要一名对手
Would that I had an opponent worthy of his interest.
我来和你比试比试
I would spar with you.
我说的是真正的角斗士
I meant a real gladiator.
Crixus的表现完美无瑕
Crixus shows impeccable form.
嗯 今晚我会在你的庆典上另行证明
Mm, I shall prove otherwise at your ceremony tonight.
还有人敢来挑战吗？
Anyone else dare challenge?
我们的战斗 还没结束
Our fight is not yet finished.
退出吧 小畜生
Stand down, pup.
别让我把你阳痿的老二打到小便失禁
Before your shriveling cock wets the sand.
他被击败了
The man is beaten.
肉体上 也许是的
In body, perhaps.
但武力
Yet confrontation
往往不能解决争斗
is often not won by force,
唯有意志
by will.
坚持下去 你这蠢货
Stay down, you ignorant shit.
够了！
Enough!
这个男人已被彻底击败 却被当成胜利者对待？
The man is soundly defeated, yet treated as victor?
这是一种尊敬
A sign of respect.
他的勇气值得钦佩
For his courage.
送他去看医生
See him to the medicus.
每天都这样吗？
Is everyday like this?
我还不知道
I was unaware you possessed
你对战棋很有两把刷子
such a skilled hand at Latrunculi.
在军事战略方面 我仍将自己看做一名学徒
Well I consider myself a student of military strategy.
为了获胜 必须设计 出其不意地捕获对手
To win, one must maneuver to catch ones opponent unawares.
战场上如此 政治上亦如是
As it is in war, so it is in politics.
嗯 又一个令我感兴趣的主题
Hm, another subject of my interest.
也许…
Perhaps…
父亲！
Father!
斯巴达克斯将他的剑给了我 我可以训练了！
Spartacus gave me his sword, so I could practice!
Numerius 你身上太脏了！
Numerius, you are filthy!
不去洗洗的话 就要结成硬壳了
I fear he will form a crust if not sent to water.
在他没有梳洗完毕前
No we shall see him well prepared
可不能出来见客了
before the guests arrive.
Naevia 护送Numerius去浴池
Naevia, escort Numerius to the bath.
是 主人
Yes, Domina.
哈！
Ah!
走过这里就到了
Just through here.
他还是太过于孩子气
There is yet much the boy in him.
最多再有一会儿罢了
For but a moment longer.
今夜Numerius将蜕变为男人
Tonight Numerius becomes a man.
洗干净了么？
Clean?
或者你还想再好好擦一下…
Or do you yet require a hard scrubbing…
不 我…
No, I am…
我…
I am…
是的
Yes, you are.
没有什么能比温暖的洗浴更令人舒适的了
Nothing more sensual than a warm bath.
水流爱抚着你的肌肤
Mm, the water caressing your skin.
你的双眼… 直勾勾地
Your eyes seem rather… fixed.
抱歉
Apologies.
无需抱歉
None required.
今夜由你主宰 Numerius
This is your night, Numerius.
在男人的一生中 有且仅有一次
One that occurs but once in a man's lifetime.
我心中充满了兴奋和刺激
I am filled with much excitement.
理所当然
Of course you are.
你的人生之卷 正在你面前展开
Your life unfolds before you.
数不清的荣耀
Many glories.
数不清的光环
Many honors.
数不清的乐事…
Many pleasures…
你今夜做出的选择
The choices you make tonight
将随着时光的流逝
will ripple through time,
改变你的宿命
altering fates and destinies.
所有这一切 都由你掌控
So much rests in your hands.
而我会妥善填满 你想要的一切…
And I would see them properly filled…
嗯 很好
Um, very nice.
而后他跳起 像这样捅了他一刀…
Then he'd jump up and stab him down like that…
对！
Yeah!
他堵住了退路…
He'd block that back…
真是一场不错的庆典啊 Batiatus！
A fine celebration, Batiatus!
我从未见他如此开怀过
I've never seen the boy so happy.
可别再叫他小男孩了
Let us call him boy no longer.
他看起来不更像一个大男人吗？
Uh, does he not appear to you a man?
他好像高了很多 不是吗？
He does seem to stand taller, does he not?
身板挺大块的
By quite some measure.
很快 他的身形将直追他伟大的父亲
Soon he will rival the stature of his honored father.
这真是让我无比自豪
It gives great pride, to know
知道Calavius家族后继有人 大道有望
I have such an heir to carry the name Calavius.
每一个家庭 都该得到这样的祝福
Every house should be so blessed.
我相信 你的儿子将会大展宏图
I believe your son will do extraordinary things.
我已经迫不及待想要看到那一天了
I for one cannot wait to see them.
给我一下 来…
Give me a go, come on…
看来 副将的老婆
It appears the wife of the Legatus
仍然心怀怨恨啊
yet harbors grudge.
她不过是只被砍了爪子的猫
She is a cat absent claws.
但还有尖牙尚存
Yet fangs remain.
感谢你昨晚的英勇
Gratitude for last night.
他越界了
The man overstepped.
我只是纠正了他的错行
I merely made correction.
尽管如此 你的心里仍然充满了友善
Still, the heart swells at such kindness.
那就看着它消失殆尽吧
Then see it deflate.
我对任何一个女人都会这样做的
I would have done the same for any woman.
你真是混蛋
You are an ass.
呃 卡普亚战神
Uh, the Champion of Capua.
真是朋友满天下啊
Always making friends.
我只需要一个
I need but one.
真幸运
Fortunate.
看来你也就这一个了
Since it appears one is all you have.
她丈夫正心急如焚！
Her husband is mad with worry!
Licinia彻底失踪了！
Licinia has completely vanished!
她在夜色中悄然离开
She slipped away in the night
没有奴隶相随 再也没人见过她
absent slaves and not seen since.
一位正派的女人 绝不该无人护送 只身外出
A proper woman should never travel without escort.
她的表亲Crassus 已重金悬赏
Her cousin good Crassus has offered
期望能够找到她的踪迹
substantial reward for her discovery.
若是她有所损伤
Larger still towards punishment
惩罚也将极其严重
if harms been done.
谁敢对Crassus的亲戚
But who would wish such a thing
做这种事呢？
upon a relation of Crassus?
真是太疯狂了
Why that would be madness.
这也揭示了 被逼到绝境之人
It is revelation what we are capable of,
所作所为会出人意料
when pushed to brink.
或是被拖入绝境之人
Or pulled.
没有丈夫和奴隶相随
Well, there can only be one cause
夜晚独自开溜
to slip out in the night,
只能有一种解释
absent slaves or husbands.
噢！
Oh!
她嫁给了一个又矮又胖的男人
She is married to a fat little man,
仅有的几根头发也是杂乱不堪
who sprouts hair as if beast.
谁能忍心责怪她呢？
Who could blame her?
迫不及待投入他人怀抱 如同海伦投怀于帕里斯一般！
Flown to the arms of another, as Helen to Paris!
哈！
Ha!
恐怕今夜罗马将黯然失色…
I fear Rome must be absent her beauty…
因为在卡普亚 共和国的珍珠
for tonight the jewels of the Republic
正在我的面前熠熠生辉
stand glittering before me in Capua.
亲爱的Solonius
Good Solonius.
你还是决定出席了
You decided to attend.
谁能抗拒如此神圣的伙伴呢？
Who could resist such divine company?
我没有眼花吧！
Do my eyes deceive!
Solonius 你终于肯现身了？
Solonius, come from the shadow to the light?
来一个兄弟般的拥抱吧！
Embrace me as brother!
愿血脉将我们紧紧相连
Would that blood were our bond.
我差点认不出你
I almost did not recognize you,
脸色太憔悴了
so gaunt of cheek.
你还好吧？
Are you quite well?
我身体好得不能再好了
My health has never been better.
悲剧啊 你在竞技场的财运 却与之南辕北辙 哈？
Sadly the same can't be said for your fortunes in the arena, huh?
有幸和行政官见过吗？
Have you had opportunity to greet the Magistrate?
我来时 他正忙着和Consularis开会呢
He was deep in conference with the Consularis when I arrived.
看在你穿了晚礼服的份上 我相信他一定会抽时间
As the evening wears, I am certain he will find time
与你这样不甚重要的客人会面的
for the less significant guests.
感谢你的邀请
Gratitude for the invitation.
希望很快 能有幸邀请您
I hope soon to return the favor.
看到他那张脸上的表情吗？
Did you see the look upon his face?
他如垂死一般龇牙咧嘴
He's the rictus of a man dying,
被狠狠地刺了一刀
a slice at a time.
我更希望给他绝命一击
I would have the fatal cut in a single stroke.
哦 我喜欢尽可能多的打击他
Oh, I prefer as many strokes as possible.
可以让快乐最大化
To maximize the pleasure.
我居然没发现 你喜欢异乡情调
I was unaware you had taste for such exotic treats.
我们在一起 不能被别人看到
We cannot be seen together.
我觉得Batiatus邀请我参加 很是奇怪
I find it curious that Batiatus would extend me invitation.
他在计划什么？
What is he planning?
在行政官面前羞辱你
To humiliate you before the Magistrate.
你主人是在玩火
Your master swims in deep waters.
要不了多久 就得玩火自焚
Some day soon he shall disappear beneath the waves.
来吧！请移步
Come! Gather,
尊敬的贵宾！
esteemed guests!
名门望族的客人们
And those of questionable repute.
今晚 Batiatus家族 不胜荣幸
Tonight the House of Batiatus is humbled
可以举行一场最荣耀的盛宴
to help celebrate a most glorious occasion.
行政官Calavius之子
The son of Magistrate Calavius,
将褪下孩童之袍
casts off the robes of a boy
行罗马成人之礼！
and becomes a proper Roman man!
在他穿上成年礼服之前
Yet before he dons the Toga Virilis,
让我们用竞技和鲜血为其致敬吧！
let us honor him with sport and blood!
前战神与现战神的交锋
A contest between the present and the past.
斯巴达克斯 卡普亚战神！
Spartacus, Champion of Capua!
走上前来！
Step forward!
还有Crixus！
And Crixus!
前战神 走…
Former Champion, step…
等等
Wait.
我担心Crixus的昔日辉煌 早已不再
I fear Crixus has seen his best day past.
我想让Varro代替他出战
I would have Varro fight in his place.
您是决策者 年轻的主人！
You are the editor, young master!
主人所愿 我之所行！
Your will, our hands!
Varro！走上前来！
Varro! Step forward!
你知道会与我对战吗？
Did you have hand in my elevation?
男孩的心思 瞬息万变
The boy's change comes as surprise.
看起来 天神现在眷顾的是我们俩啊
It seems the gods favor us both now.
向男孩致敬
Honor the boy.
为训练场添光
Honor the ludus.
Numerius在我们自己家里侮辱Crixus！
Numerius insults Crixus in our own house!
先不管它
Let it pass.
行政官的欢心才是我们的目的
The Magistrate's happiness is our only concern.
Numerius 来吧！
Come Numerius!
这些男人 竞技场的巨人 都在等候你的号令！
These men, these titans of the arena, await your command!
让我们展示一下吧
Let us give them a show.
开始！
Begin!
哦！
Oh!
我他妈的侧面！
My fucking flank!
保护好 下次胜利的可能就是你了
Protect it, and next time it may be you who stands victorious.
斯巴达克斯 依旧是卡普亚的战神！
Spartacus, still the Champion of Capua!
而Varro 是强大的对手
And Varro, formidable opponent,
需要密切关注的竞技场人物！
one to watch closely in the arena!
有请Numerius！
Come Numerius!
请决定战败斗士的生死吧！
Pass judgment on our fallen warrior!
抱歉 行政官
Apologies, Magistrate,
说好了 这只是一场展示赛
it was agreed this was an exhibition only.
而不是生死决斗
Not a fight to the death.
父亲…
Father…
Numerius已经做了决定
Numerius has made his decision.
我会赔偿你的损失
I will reimburse you the cost of the man.
继续
Proceed.
有什么问题吗 Batiatus？
Do we have a problem, Batiatus?
我说了 继续
I said proceed.
不要…
Don't…
不要
Don't.
他们会杀死我们俩的
They will kill us both.
没得选择
There is no choice.
选择一直都有
There is always a choice.
但不是这次
Not this time.
斯巴达克斯！
Spartacus!
活下去…
Live…
照顾我的家人
And see my family provided for.
你知道…
And know…
我也会这么做的…
I would have done the same…
您的款待 我将永远铭记于心 Batiatus
I am forever indebted to your hospitality, Batiatus.
您不必放在心上
Think nothing of it.
为朋友 在所不辞
A favor for a dear friend.
他判定生死 毫不迟疑！
He calls for blood without hesitation!
他的大胆 终会让他跻身元老院
Such boldness will one day lead him to the senate.
高贵的野心
The noblest of ambitions.
我自己对行政官职也有所希冀
I myself have designs towards political office.
是吗？
Is that so?
哦 不是元老院 也不会这么早
Well, not the senate, not so soon,
只是当地的职位
but something local.
我希望得到您的支持 也许明天…
I would speak to you of support, perhaps tomorrow…
因为公事 我要动身到海岸去
I leave for the coast on business.
那就等您回来吧
Well, when you return then.
政治对你这样擅于游说的人来说 太无趣了！
Politics is too dull for a man of your persuasion!
你会想念竞技场的呼声和风采
You would ache for the sights and sounds of the arena.
为了服务罗马 我很乐意牺牲
A sacrifice I would gladly make in the service to Rome.
Batiatus 你是个优秀的角斗士主人
Batiatus, you are a fine lanista.
或许是全共和国最优秀的
Perhaps the finest in all the Republic.
但是政治嘛…
But politics…
需要其他的品质
It requires a different sort.
身份地位 还有适当的财产
Citizens of status, with the proper heritage.
就是这样
Just so.
尽情享受你在行的东西吧
Relish what you know best.
把政治留给那些为此而生的人们
Leave politics to the men with breeding for it.
来吧 Solonius！
Come, good Solonius!
我们今晚还没好好说过话呢
We have not had occasion to speak this evening.
行政官反应如何？
The Magistrate's response?
刺得我鲜血淋漓
To be answered in blood.